<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Rickard's personal homepage: latest posts tagged newsletter</title>
        <link>http://rickardlindberg.me</link>
        <description><![CDATA[Rickard's personal homepage: latest posts tagged newsletter]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://rickardlindberg.me/tags/newsletter/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>February 2023 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/february-2023/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>February 2023 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  5 March 2023.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in February 2023:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I started reading <a href="https://joyofagility.com/">Joy of Agility</a>. It has many interesting stories that provide valuable lessons.</p></li>
<li><p>I continued writing my blog post <a href="/writing/what-should-a-ci-server-do/index.html">What should a Continuous Integration (CI) server do?</a>. I also asked for feedback on <a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/">James’</a> Discord server and got many useful responses. In particular i learned about <a href="https://www.eficode.com/blog/pre-tested-integration">pre-tested integration</a> which looks very similar to what I tried to describe. I will update my blog post with feedback, and then I will call it done.</p></li>
<li><p>I <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@rickardlindberg/109846707922919650">asked Allen Holub</a> how to think about work that is not a story. Agile is about constantly providing value via stories, but what about work that needs to be done that doesn’t fit that category?</p></li>
<li><p>I read <a href="https://computerhistory.org/blog/postscript-a-digital-printing-press/">PostScript: A Digital Printing Press</a>. It was a bit of computer history that I enjoyed.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another two programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/2VrKIIMTFUI">What should a Continuous Integration (CI) server do?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/_uB1KGPjJjw">How TDD helps me solve programming problems.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/february-2023/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>January 2023 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/january-2023/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>January 2023 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on 11 February 2023.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in January 2023:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I started working on my <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/projects">ideal code hosting platform</a>. I’ve attempted to do this once before and failed. I got the urge to give it another try. With my new experience of working in an agile way, I think my chance of succeeding this time is higher. But as always, you need to keep working on the project if it’s not going to die. Anyway, I am happy with the experience of trying and will for sure learn something.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/yXrY5pT88vA">AgileByExample 2021: J.B. Rainsberger - Unlocking the Awesome Power of Refactoring</a>. I learned about the idea of practice. If something you do regularly requires conscious brain effort, practice it until it becomes boring. That frees up brain capacity to think about more high-level problems.</p></li>
<li><p>I started reading <em>Extreme Programming Explained</em> (Second Edition) by Kent Beck. I wanted to learn more about XP since it seems to be the origin of “real” agile. I wanted to learn more about how accurate <a href="https://twitter.com/christianhujer/status/1614888741126176771">this tweet</a> was:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>• DevOps is just whole team+CI from XP.<br> • Teaming is whole team+pair programming from XP.<br> • TBD is just CI from XP.<br> • BDD is TDD+ATDD from XP.<br> <br> ⇒ 20+ years later, XP is still leading the way.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>I made some progress on my thinking about continuous integration and have a post about it in progress titled <a href="/writing/what-should-a-ci-server-do/index.html">What should a Continuous Integration (CI) server do?</a></p></li>
<li><p>I published another two programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/Hdg0LNga2dQ">My experience of one year on Youtube.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/ZvowW_toPmQ">How I start a new programming project. Building my ideal code hosting platform.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/january-2023/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>December 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/december-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>December 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  9 January 2023.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in December 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I finished writing my blog post <a href="/writing/evolving-design-of-projectional-editor/index.html">How should I evolve the design of my projectional editor?</a></p></li>
<li><p>I studied <a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/v2/projects/testing-without-mocks/testing-without-mocks">Testing Without Mocks: A Pattern Language</a> a bit more as James published a draft update of his article. I also watched some episodes of <a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/v2/projects/nullables-livestream">Nullables &amp; A-Frame Architecture Livestream</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I got the urge to build a new home for <a href="/projects/timeline/index.html">Timeline</a>. Many years ago a <a href="/writing/new-home-for-timeline/index.html">wrote</a> about what I want from a new home. I have tried building it once before but failed. Now with my updated knowledge of Agile development, I think I might be able to pull it off. (But most likely I will fail again. If I try.)</p></li>
<li><p>I solved Advent of Code <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2022/day/17">day 17</a> and published my <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/aoc/blob/main/2022/17.py">solution</a> on Github.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another two programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/PG3XvSd7Mns">This refactoring uncovered another problem.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/AuuLTUSfBjs">How blogging helped me solve a programming problem.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/december-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>November 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/november-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>November 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  2 December 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in November 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I continued programming on my <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlproject">projectional editor</a>. I had so many ideas I wanted to try, but I got stuck with the design. I started writing a <a href="/writing/evolving-design-of-projectional-editor/index.html">blog post</a> explaining the problem. The blog post helped me get unstuck and I was able to move forward with my ideas.</p></li>
<li><p>I struggled with my writing in the before mentioned blog post. I got a <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@estherschindler/109424345364034217">tip</a> to read a book called “Bird by Bird”. It is a bit unlike other books I usually read in that it paints a picture of what it is like to be a writer. It doesn’t just give you the facts how to become a (better) writer. Sometimes I enjoy it and sometimes I just want the facts.</p></li>
<li><p>I created a Mastodon account to explore this other federated version of microblogging. You can find me at <a
href="https://hachyderm.io/@rickardlindberg"><span class="citation" data-cites="rickardlindberg">@rickardlindberg</span><span class="citation" data-cites="hachyderm.io">@hachyderm.io</span></a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I published just one programming video on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/qa_2Bk4bLyw">My projectional editor can do this now?!</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/november-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>October 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/october-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>October 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on 10 November 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in October 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I started exploring projectional editing with <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlproject">rlproject</a>. For now, I’m trying to implement something like what <a href="https://github.com/projectured/projectured/wiki">ProjecturEd</a> describes in its documentation to learn how that might work.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/8Ab3ArE8W3s">“Stop Writing Dead Programs” by Jack Rusher (Strange Loop 2022)</a>. It showed what a better development environment might look like. It also showed that a projectional editor might make your program feel more alive than a plain text editor. Hillel Wayne <a href="https://www.hillelwayne.com/post/strangeloop-22/">points out</a> that the talk has factual errors. Nevertheless, I found it inspiring.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/Fk4rCn4YLLU">End to end functional tests that can run in milliseconds | Nat Pryce | CukenFest London 2017</a>. Nat showed an interesting approach to testing you application in a flexible way.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/9fJntxnH4wY">Pairin’ with Aaron: Messing with Language Servers</a>. I learned about languages servers (LPS’s) and their integration with the development environment.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched some episodes of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCgt1lVMrdwlZKBaerxxp2iQ">Mob Mentality Show</a> and found them interesting.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another four programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/DowzqlHr67k">Writing and testing a tiny application without mocks.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/3060LO0PZaY">I demo a tool that makes me super quick at the command line and more.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/1_LAeMUdbH0">How to check balanced string TDD style + a bonus.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/GUX3DQjVg4c">Demo of new project that explores projectional, structured editing.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/october-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>September 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/september-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>September 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  8 October 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in September 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I finally finished writing <a href="/writing/reliable-socket-servers/index.html">How to write reliable socket servers that survive crashes and restarts?</a></p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/ulRCs7xQA74">Continuous Delivery vs. Gitflow &amp; CD At Scale | Bryan Finster In The Engineering Room Ep. 11</a>. In it, Bryan mention a metaphor with flying cards. The idea was that it is difficult to explain the concept of a flying car to someone who has never experienced it. It’s too foreign. I thought about how I could expose people to more “flying cars”. Make them experience TDD, CI/CD, etc, so that they never wanting to go back.</p></li>
<li><p>I think it was also in the video above that Dave said something along the lines that it’s amazing how much you start caring about testing if you are the one on call. That resonated with me. If you are responsible, you start caring. It also reminded me of another concept about how much to test, where the advice was something like test until fear turns into boredom. (I think I read it from <a href="https://twitter.com/jbrains">jbrains</a>, but <a href="https://twitter.com/jbrains/status/663451314341416960">it seems</a> to originally be from someone else.)</p></li>
<li><p>I published another five programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/tu3Sbm78SpY">How to write reliable socket servers that survive crashes and restarts?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/X5yIEELf4t0">What does working in small steps look like?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/IWAx1-thc_w">Are you running your tests often enough?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/1bDEHWKjbyQ">My continuous integration workflow.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/kdYE7_9-5Ng">My workflow for making changes to software.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/september-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>August 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/august-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>August 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  9 September 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in August 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I was interested in learning more how to slice stories to make them smaller but still valuable. I found Ron’s article <a href="https://ronjeffries.com/xprog/articles/getting-small-stories/">Getting Small Stories</a> very useful. Having one “dumb” idea can change the conversation from “that is impossible” to “how can we make it better”.</p></li>
<li><p>I also read Ron’s book <a href="https://pragprog.com/titles/rjnsd/the-nature-of-software-development/">The Nature of Software Development</a>. In it he talks about focusing on value and that value is something that <em>we want</em>. But who is <em>we</em>? When I am working on software that I use, I can ask myself what I want. But in most cases I’m not the only user of the software that I write. <em>We</em> are probably many different people.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve though about writing a book about how to implement programming languages. It would use <a href="/projects/rlmeta/index.html">RLMeta</a> for the examples. But writing a book seems like a daunting task. I started thinking that I could approach writing the book the same way I approach writing software in an agile fashion with small stories. I can create the first version of the “book” in one day. Then I can improve it by writing more chapters and going into more details.</p></li>
<li><p>I continued writing <a href="/writing/reliable-socket-servers/index.html">How to write reliable socket servers that survive crashes and restarts?</a></p></li>
<li><p>I watched the Mob Mentality Show <a href="https://youtu.be/nLUFPHUS2Pk">Agile vs. Agility with Allen Holub</a>. I’ve been inspired by Allen’s talk about Agile, and I got value from this episode.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another four programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/BXyiqhqXT0U">I did the simplest thing that could possibly work. Here’s what happened.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/XldYdxAlH2o">Converting RLCI to client/server architecture (part 1/3).</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/9HQB9pt4v30">Converting RLCI to client/server architecture (part 2/3).</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/GBfUerlQfuI">Converting RLCI to client/server architecture (part 3/3).</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/august-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>July 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/july-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>July 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  2 August 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in July 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I continued practicing Agile software development with <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlci/">RLCI</a>. I slowly get the feeling that Agile is not really what most people think it is. Some things I read and watched this month in that vein:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>A <a href="https://twitter.com/allenholub/status/1546604233323032576">few</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/allenholub/status/1552432052762320896">tweets</a> by Allen Holub and a <a href="https://youtu.be/hxXmTnb3mFU">conversation</a> he had with Dave Farley gave me some insights into what “real” Agile is about.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.sicpers.info/2022/07/phrases-in-computing-that-might-need-retiring/">Phrases in computing that might need retiring</a> by Graham Lee indicated to me that the term “Agile” has changed meaning over the years.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.ronjeffries.com/articles/-z022/0222ff/gotta-be-good/">Gotta Be Good</a> by Ron Reffries indicated to me that “real” Agile is actually HARD and need to be practiced to get good at.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>I published another five programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/d7fq8JyU9jg">How to write tests that allow refactoring your code?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/BmUz4my7eko">Deploying my continuous integration software to a server.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/C05OD7h0-gg">Therapeutic refactoring and polishing of a feature.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/h_oRLiJo3Tc">How to incorporate evolutionary design into the development process?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/WlvsjCeuT6w">I made a mistake when evolving the design of RLCI to support a database.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/july-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>June 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/june-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>June 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  4 July 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in June 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I started over with <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlci/">RLCI</a> and tried to build it using an agile approach. The README has a bunch of more information about it. In this process, the following resources helped me:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/v2/blog/2018/testing-without-mocks">Testing Without Mocks: A Pattern Language</a> Again from James Shore. Gave me insight into how to design and test.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://blog.thecodewhisperer.com/permalink/you-dont-hate-mocks-you-hate-side-effects">You Don’t Hate Mocks; You Hate Side-Effects</a> The following quote explained it well to me the design relationship between pure functions and functions with side effects:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We always have the option of replacing a side-effect with returning a value that represents the effect, as long as we can instruct the clients to interpret that value as a command to execute.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p><a href="https://stackoverflow.blog/2022/01/03/favor-real-dependencies-for-unit-testing/">Favor real dependencies for unit testing</a> This helped me solve a testing problem I had. More on that in an upcoming video.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>I discovered that one of the authors of <em>Continuous Delivery</em>, Dave Farley, has a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/ContinuousDelivery">Youtube channel</a>. I found some of his videos interesting.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another four programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/yKkGXn1zmaI">How James Shore ruined my RLCI project.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/Re7litDdulU">Rebooting RLCI with an agile approach using TDD and zero friction development.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/sokSvnAkd5E">Adding continuous integration functionality to RLCI.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/0jJEPgomRCc">Making RLCI pipelines run in isolation.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/june-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>May 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/may-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>May 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  4 June 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in May 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I rediscovered James Shore through his <a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/v2/books/aoad2/book_club/evolutionary_design">Agile Book Club: Evolutionary Design (with Kent Beck)</a>. I had stumbled upon his <a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/v2/projects/lunch-and-learn">TDD Lunch &amp; Learn</a> series before, and the book club made me revisit some of his work. This time I also bought his book <a href="https://www.jamesshore.com/v2/books/aoad2">The Art of Agile Development</a> which reignited my interest for agile methods (something that has diminished more and more since I first got into it).</p></li>
<li><p>I read <a href="https://alangrow.com/blog/dream-deploys-atomic-zero-downtime-deployments">Dream Deploys: Atomic, Zero-Downtime Deployments</a> and got inspired to try that approach. I also started working on a <a href="/writing/reliable-socket-servers/index.html">blog post</a> on my own to explore the topic.</p></li>
<li><p>I continued working on <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlci/">RLCI</a> and worked on connecting the different pieces. However, after getting inspired by agile methods again and learning that continuous integration is not what I thought it was (thanks for the inspiration James!), I will have to rethink the project. I think I will start over from scratch and develop it with a slightly new approach.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another four programming videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4XI09URnsM_YYTSizAMliA">Youtube channel</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/R-HCtiVzYuI">Connecting all the pieces in RLCI.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/BQ-wWIVQ_gs">Researching zero downtime deployments.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/S_R80ZhsmZo">Getting back to the roots of TDD.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/Xm8QGMzyxeI">Practicing TDD and testing without mocks.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/may-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>April 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/april-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>April 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  1 May 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in April 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I continued working on <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlci/">RLCI</a>. In particular I started working on the server component and wrote it using <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/asyncio.html">asyncio</a>. So far, that feels like a good choice.</p></li>
<li><p>I read <a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/books/refactoringDatabases.html">Refactoring databases</a> and started reading <a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/books/nosql.html">NoSQL Distilled</a>. The reason I picked up the first one was that I sought to understand how you can do zero-downtime deployments and still evolve your database. That is, how can both an old version of an application and a new version of an application work with the same database? The answer was that you must evolve your database schema such that it is compatible with both versions. So if you move a column for example, you can create a trigger that make sure that both the old and the new column are in sync. And when a transition period is over, you can drop the old column, and the move column refactoring is complete. I picked up the second book to find if the answer was any different for NoSQL databases which generally are a bit more flexible when it comes to database schema. My guess is that a similar approach is needed. So far the book has given me some new ideas about what databases are for and how different databases serve different purposes. This will all be useful in going forward with a storage mechanism for RCLI.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another five programming videos on my Youtube channel:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/lqV5c_fN29Q">How to find time to work on your hobby projects?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/aXkGdvKZu1A">How I got unstuck with RLCI.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/GO-sfUaqbvg">Learning Python asyncio when working on CI server.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/ihS0HagBfKY">What makes programming videos interesting?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/uV2eeAcrxzU">Refactoring a class to test in isolation: REAL WORLD EXAMPLE</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/april-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>March 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/march-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>March 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  2 April 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in March 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I started prototyping <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlci/">RLCI</a> which is an experimental CI/CD system designed to solve problems I’ve had with Jenkins. I made some videos about it too.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another four programming videos on my Youtube channel:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/pZwjYknDxYo">Sharing thoughts about a new CI system that solves problems I’ve had with Jenkins.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/-iSgZkqlUVw">Thinking about representations for CI pipelines.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/oPX8bBTNBMI">Demoing prototype of CI/CD system.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/RHy-oryo5rI">How can a worker node execute code on behalf of a CI/CD server?</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/march-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>February 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/february-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>February 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  2 March 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in February 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I finished the blog post about the new version of <a href="/writing/rlmeta-poster-2/index.html">RLMeta</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I published another four programming videos on my Youtube channel:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/stBGg7v-URg">How I got consumed by a programming problem and recovered.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/ACTO7AfB_zQ">Adding LISP-style function calls to RLMeta.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/riJUqBPx1uU">Solving Advent of Code 2021 Day 14 using Python without any libraries.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/84IUZVyFrh8">Demoing new image export dialog in Timeline version 2.6.0.</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/february-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>January 2022 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/january-2022/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>January 2022 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  4 February 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in January 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I did more writing on the <a href="/writing/rlmeta-poster-2/index.html">RLMeta</a> blog post. I took some larger time blocks to work on it, and I can now finally see it being finished next month.</p></li>
<li><p>I decided to set up a <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/rlmeta">repo on GitHub</a> for RLMeta where it can continue to be improved. I plan for it to contain the base version of RLMeta which is the minimal version that is able to compile itself and maintain properties such as flexible, easy to extend, and easy to understand. Then I want to include examples as well to show how RLMeta can be used and how you can extend it in various ways.</p></li>
<li><p>I started publishing weekly programming videos on Youtube. My goal for 2022 is to make one programming related video each week. I’m currently in the process of finding a good format or formats, and I am experimenting a lot. This month I made the following videos:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/NsVERD6Xvvw">I’m starting weekly programming videos on Youtube.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/6lqdJvSuZpk">How a Python programmer extracts timelapses from camera SD card.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/aT2XbyMv53E">Writing a decoder for the “Quite OK Image Format” (QOI) in 55 lines of RLMeta.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/V3oUnhyCSkY">Rewriting QOI decoder semantic action in Python for clarity and speed.</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>I got an urge to write a projectional editor to learn more about projectional editing. It’s something I’ve been thinking about before and have tried to incorporate a bit in <a href="/projects/rliterate/index.html">RLiterate</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/dP1xVpMPn8M">A Tour of the Acme Editor</a> by Russ Cox. Acme felt like a different and unique text editor with an interesting approach.</p></li>
<li><p>I did some work to update my <a href="https://github.com/rickardlindberg/dotfiles/">dotfiles</a>. Mainly to simplify and add support for different setups. When I am recording videos for Youtube, for example, I want to have bigger font size in various applications. With my new dotfiles, I can now quickly switch between different setups.</p></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/january-2022/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>December 2021 Update</title>
    <link>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/december-2021/</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1>December 2021 Update</h1>

<p><em>Published on  4 January 2022.</em></p>

<p>This is what I’ve been up to in December 2021:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>I did more writing on the <a href="/writing/rlmeta-poster-2/index.html">RLMeta</a> blog post. I wrote for quite many days, but not for a very long time each day. I believe consistency works better. After each small edit, I published the draft. I will continue writing in January.</p></li>
<li><p>After quite a long absence, I made a contribution to <a href="/projects/timeline/index.html">Timeline</a> again. The contribution was to replace all image export dialogs with a better, more flexible one. I got inspired to work on this because of a problem that a user expressed on the mailing list. The new dialog will hopefully make the user experience a bit better and it simplified the code base. After the initial version, I had to make tweaks to make it work good on both Linux and Windows. Even though wxPython is cross-platform, you can still run into issues that are platform specific.</p></li>
<li><p>I started planning and recording a series of programming videos that I will publish on Youtube. My goal for 2022 is to publish one video every week. More on that in the first video, which I have planned for 7th of January.</p></li>
<li><p>I watched <a href="https://youtu.be/GgsRQuGSrc0">Building an encoder for the “Quite OK Image Format” (QOI)</a>. It inspired me to try and write a QOI decoder in RLMeta. I plan to make a video about that.</p></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://rickardlindberg.me/writing/newsletter/december-2021/</guid>
    <dc:creator>Rickard Lindberg</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
